During a long day spent roaming the forest
in search of edible grains and herbs,
the weary /ˈwɪərɪ 疲倦的/ divine /dɪˈvaɪn 神的/ farmer Shennong
accidentally poisoned himself 72 times.
But before the poisons could end his life,
a leaf drifted /drɪft 漂/ into his mouth.
He chewed /tʃuː/ on it and it revived /rɪˈvaɪv 复活/ him,
and that is how we discovered tea.
Or so an ancient /ˈeɪnʃənt/ legend /ˈlɛdʒənd/ goes at least.
Tea doesn't actually cure /kjʊə 治疗/ poisonings,
but the story of Shennong,
the mythical /ˈmɪθɪkəl 神话的/ Chinese inventor
of agriculture,
highlights tea's importance
to ancient China.
Archaeological /ˌɑːkɪəˈlɒdʒɪkəl 考古学的/ evidence /ˈɛvɪdəns/ suggests tea
was first cultivated there
as early as 6,000 years ago,
or 1,500 years before the pharaohs /ˈfeərəʊ 法老/ built
the Great Pyramids /ˈpɪrəmɪd/ of Giza.
That original Chinese tea plant
is the same type that's grown
around the world today,
yet it was originally consumed
very differently.
It was eaten as a vegetable
or cooked with grain porridge /ˈpɒrɪdʒ 粥/.
Tea only shifted from food
to drink 1,500 years ago
when people realized that a combination
of heat and moisture /ˈmɔɪstʃə 潮气/
could create a complex and varied /ˈvɛərɪ 改变/ taste
out of the leafy green.
After hundreds of years of variations /ˌvɛərɪˈeɪʃən 改变/
to the preparation method,
the standard became to heat tea,
pack it into portable cakes,
grind /ɡraɪnd 磨，碾/ it into powder,
mix with hot water,
and create a beverage
called muo cha, or matcha.
Matcha became so popular that a distinct /dɪˈstɪŋkt/
Chinese tea culture emerged /ɪˈmɜːdʒ/.
Tea was the subject of books and poetry /ˈpəʊɪtrɪ 诗歌/,
the favorite drink of emperors /ˈempərə 皇帝/,
and a medium /ˈmiːdɪəm 媒介/ for artists.
They would draw extravagant /ɪkˈstrævəɡənt 奢侈的/ pictures
in the foam of the tea,
very much like the espresso /eˈspresəʊ 浓咖啡/ art
you might see in coffee shops today.
In the 9th century
during the Tang Dynasty /ˈdaɪnəsti/,
a Japanese monk /mʌŋk 和尚/ brought the first
tea plant to Japan.
The Japanese eventually developed
their own unique rituals /ˈrɪtjʊəl 习惯的/ around tea,
leading to the creation
of the Japanese tea ceremony /ˈsɛrəmənɪ 典礼/.
And in the 14th century
during the Ming Dynasty /ˈdaɪnəsti/,
the Chinese emperor /ˈempərə/
shifted the standard
from tea pressed into cakes
to loose leaf tea.
At that point, China still held a
virtual /ˈvɜːtʃʊəl 实质上的/ monopoly /məˈnɒpəlɪ  垄断/ on the world's tea trees,
making tea one of three
essential Chinese export goods,
along with porcelain /ˈpɔːslɪn 瓷器/ and silk.
This gave China a great deal of power
and economic /i英 e美/ influence /ˈɪnflʊəns/
as tea drinking spread around the world.
That spread began /bɪˈɡæn/ in earnest /ˈɜːnɪst 认真的/
around the early 1600s
when Dutch /dʌtʃ 荷兰人/ traders brought tea to Europe
in large quantities /ˈkwɒntɪtɪ 大量/.
Many credit Queen Catherine of Braganza,
a Portuguese /ˌpɔːtjʊˈɡiːz/ noble /ˈnəʊbəl  贵族/ woman,
for making tea popular with
the English aristocracy /ˌærɪˈstɒkrəsɪ 贵族（阶层），上层社会 /
when she married King Charles II in 1661.
At the time, Great Britain was in the
midst /mɪdst 在…中间/ of expanding its colonial /kəˈləʊnɪəl 殖民的/ influence
and becoming the new dominant /ˈdɒmɪnənt 支配的/ world power.
And as Great Britain grew,
interest in tea spread around the world.
By 1700, tea in Europe sold for ten times
the price of coffee
and the plant was still
only grown in China.
The tea trade was so lucrative /ˈluːkrətɪv 赚大钱的/
that the world's fastest sailboat /seilbəut 帆船/,
the clipper /ˈklɪpə 快速帆船/ship,
was born out of intense competition
between Western trading companies.
All were racing to bring their tea
back to Europe first
to maximize /ˈmæksɪˌmaɪz/ their profits.
At first, Britain paid
for all this Chinese tea with silver /ˈsɪlvə/.
When that proved /pruːvd/ too expensive,
they suggested trading tea
for another substance /ˈsʌbstəns 物质/, opium /ˈəʊpɪəm 鸦片/.
This triggered a public health problem
within China
as people became addicted /əˈdɪktɪd 上瘾的/ to the drug.
Then in 1839, a Chinese official
ordered his men
to destroy massive  /ˈmæsɪv/
British shipments of opium /ˈəʊpɪəm 鸦片/
as a statement against
Britain's influence over China.
This act triggered the First Opium War
between the two nations.
Fighting raged /reɪdʒ 愤怒/ up and down
the Chinese coast until 1842
when the defeated /dɪˈfiːt/ Qing Dynasty ceded /siːd 割让/
the port of Hong Kong to the British
and resumed /rɪˈzjuːm 摘要/ trading on unfavorable terms.
The war weakened China's global standing
for over a century.
The British East India company also
wanted to be able to grow tea themselves
and further control the market.
So they commissioned /kəˈmɪʃən 委托/
botanist /ˈbɒtənɪst 植物学家/ Robert Fortune
to steal tea from China
in a covert /ˈkʌvət 隐蔽的/ operation.
He disguised /dɪsˈɡaɪzd 伪装/ himself
and took a perilous /ˈpɛrɪləs 危险的/ journey
through China's mountainous tea regions,
eventually smuggling /ˈsmʌɡəl 走私/ tea trees
and experienced tea workers
into Darjeeling, India.
From there,
the plant spread further still,
helping drive tea's rapid growth
as an everyday commodity /kəˈmɒdɪtɪ 商品/.
Today, tea is the second most consumed
beverage in the world after water,
and from sugary Turkish Rize tea,
to salty Tibetan butter tea,
there are almost as many ways
of preparing the beverage
as there are cultures on the globe.